诸神字幕组 www.kamigami.org
日听：NEKO 翻译&校对：小卷 压制&发布：娜夏大人
Studio Rikka
In the future, probably Japan.
“Robots” have seen practical use for some time.
This is an era just after the widespread deployment of “Androids.”
情報発信源を特定しました
We’ve identified the information source.
As expected, it’s from the same district.
やはり同じ地区です
今回は五体以上のアンドロイドを経由しています
This time it was transmitted via more than five other androids.
パターン 分岐しました
Somehow, the pattern diverged.
尚　やは…
Just as we tho—
受信画だけをトレースして
Trace the recipient unit.
受信機体　特定しました
Recipient identified.
こちらでもモニターした
I’ve found it on my end as well.
驚いた
I’m surprised.
この機体　潮月の置き土産ね
That is Shiotsuki’s parting gift, isn’t it?
と言いますと?
What are you trying to say?
潮月のAI－code:LIFE の実装実験　覚えてる?
Shiotsuki’s ai, Code:life—do you recall that implementation experiment?
主任が強制停止したあれですか
The one that you forcefully halted?
再稼動中とは知りませんでした
I didn’t know it had been continued.
それも施設外で
And externally, too.
関係職員宅にて保護観察中
All related personnel are under protective observation.
思わぬところで繋がったよね
It’s all connected in ways I had not foreseen.
いずれにせよ　この地区一帯のアンドロイドがあの店の情報を得ているのはほぼ確定
In any case,
it’s almost certain that the androids in this district are receiving messages from that café.
しかも彼ら同士の会話で
And all via communication among their own kind.
潮月　これもあなたの仕業なの
Is this your doing as well, Shiotsuki?
該当機体の現在位置　トレース開始します
Now tracing the location of the unit in question.
Time of EVE
ログは正常に書き出されました　マスター
The log has been successfully written, Master.
質問
Question.
何でしょうか
What is it?
いや…
Well …
質問キャンセル
Cancel question.
コーヒー
Coffee.
Acknowledged.
かしこまりました
みんなは…じゃなくて
Where is—I mean,
ステータス:家族
Status: Family.
お父様は仕事場に宿泊されています
Your father has taken up residence at his workplace.
お母様は私の復帰時刻よりもはやくお出かけになりました
Your mother left before my activation.
ナオコ様はまだ就寝中と思われます
I believe Naoko-sama is still in bed.
帰宅時間
Time of return.
午前3時18分です
3:18 a.m.
ああ　気持ち悪い
I feel terrible.
Then you shouldn’t have gone drinking.
なら飲まなきゃいいじゃん
最初は気持ちいいの
It felt good at first.
Order your own coffee!
自分で頼んでよコーヒー
飲み会のあとさ　迎えに来たのよこれ
After the party, this thing came to pick me up.
めちゃくちゃ恥ずかしかったんだけど
I was so embarrassed.
朝食はいかがいたしますか
What about breakfast?
朝食キャンセル
Cancel breakfast.
申し訳ありません　もう一度お願いします
I am really sorry.
Could you please repeat—
朝食一人分　今すぐ
One serving of breakfast immediately.
かしこまりました
Acknowledged.
日本国内における食料自給率が8割を超えたことが明らかになりました
Our domestic food self-sufficiency ratio will soon exceed 80%.
Domestic food self-sufficiency ratio exceeds 80%
これは食料管理省の調べによ…
Agricultural Ministry
The biggest pace of expansion since robot
labor was introduced into primary industries.
This is the finding from an investigation by the Agricultural Ministry—
Would you eat a tomato created by machines?
In such an age, treasure warmth.
Ethics Committee
Whoa! In other words, “dori-kei” refers to a psychological dependence on androids, yes?
つまりドリ系とは　アンドロイド精神依存症からきているんですねですね
最近では　ハウスロイドを人間視してしまう若者をこう呼ぶんですけれども
Recently, this is what young people who treat house-roids as humans are being called.
そんなドリ系と呼ばれる人たちを取材しました
We bring you our investigation of these “dori-kei” people.
きもい　どっか行ってって感じ
Ah, how gross! They should just like … clear off.
They were all arm-in-arm and stuff.
なんか腕組んで…
Whoa, that’s intense!
きつっ
寂しいんじゃないの　友達とかもいなくて
Isn’t it just loneliness? Like if they don’t have any friends …
あんたも気付けてよね
You should be careful too.
What do you mean by that?
気付けてってなんだよ
… Just order it around.
リクオ
Rikuo. I saw your sister yesterday.
昨日お前の姉ちゃん見たぞ
夜中でしょう
Midnight, right?
改札で　かなり酔ってた
At the station turnstiles. She was pretty drunk.
ちゃんと迎えに行ったって
She was properly escorted.
You went?
お前が?
ちのアンドロイド
Our android did.
Like I said …
だからさ…
お前はロボット信用しすぎだつーの
You trust robots way too much.
別に信用してるわけじゃないけどさ
It’s not really a matter of trust.
ほらなんとか原則
Come on. The whatever laws.
The three laws of robotics.
ロボット三原則
First Law.
第一条
Do not inflict injury on humans. Protect humans.
人間に危害を加えない　人間を守る
Oh. Is that why it went to pick her up?
それで迎えに行ったのか
人間を心配してるわけじゃねぇんだ
It’s not like they worry about humans.
持ってんならその辺考えろよ
You have an android;
at least think about these things.
持ってない奴がよく言うよ
You’re one to talk. You don’t even have one.
ね　これどう思う
Hey, what do you think about this?
数字が並んでる
It’s a bunch of numbers.
行動記録
These are movement records for my android.
うちのアンドロイドの
どの辺が?
Which part?
このあと暇?
Are you free after this?
ちょっと付き合ってほしいんだけど
I want you to come with me.
どこに
Where to?
それが…分かんない
That’s … I don’t know.
なんだそれ
What’s up with that?
最近様子が変でさ　帰宅時間がばらついてたり
It has been acting strange recently, coming home at weird hours.
お前んちのロボット?
Your robot?
それで気になって調べたんだよ行動記録
So I got concerned and looked into its movement records.
そしたら
And …?
20時間前だから
Twenty hours ago; that’d be yesterday afternoon?
昨日の昼過ぎかな
勝手に寄り道してた
It went off on its own.
That’s because … it had things to do, right?
そりゃ…
用事があったんだろう
ここで?
Here?
マジでここ?
Here? Seriously?
You’re lost
I wonder if the gps’s calibration is off?
GPSずれてるのかな
ロボットが来る場所じゃねぇだろう
This isn’t a place that robots would come to.
おい
Hey.
怪しくね?
Doesn’t it seem suspicious?
If we don’t go in …
そりゃ入ってみないと
怪しいかな
It is kinda suspicious.
じゃ帰るか
Then should we go home?
Time of Eve’s Rule
In this café,
there is to be no discrimination
between humans and robots.
Customers, please cooperate
Obey the rule and have a fun time... Nagi
これって
This is—
Welcome!
いらっしゃいませ
空いてる席にどうぞ
Please take any seat that’s free.
注文取りに行くから
I’ll take your orders soon.
はい　そっちね
Right. Over there, yeah?
It might only be a short while,
短い時間かもしれないけど
but enjoy yourselves, all right?
楽しんでってね
喫茶店?
A café?
喫茶店だな
It’s a café.
アンドロイドが喫茶店に
Androids going to a café?
They might not be here to drink tea.
別にお茶しに来たわけじゃねぇだろう
それよか　あのルール…
More importantly, that rule.
やっぱりヤバイの
Seems pretty dangerous.
ロボット法的には
Under robot legislation, this is …
considered the grey zone.
グレーゾーンだな
表現が曖昧すぎる
It’s too vague.
って聞けよおい
Listen to me!
It’s here.
いた
What?
なんだよ
Isn’t that the android from just now?
さっきのアンドロイド あれだよね
リングがない
There’s no ring.
マジかよ
You can’t be serious.
Is this … in the grey zone?
これってグレーゾーン
Have you ever seen a robot without a ring?
リングのないロボット見たことあるか
超ロボット法違反
This is a serious breach of robot legislation.
人間と区別付かなくなっとる
You can’t even distinguish them from humans!
なんだあいつ
Who the hell is he?
ご注文は
Your order?
This. Eve Blend.
この…イヴブレンド
Evlend.
イヴレンド
それ
That.
I’ll have one too.
同じく
イヴレツー
Two Evlends!
Obey the rule, all right?
ルールは守ってね
Ah. I just thought of something unpleasant.
嫌なこと思いついた
何
What?
このカフェのルール
This place’s rule.
人間とロボット区別しない
“No discrimination between humans and robots”?
だからリングがない
That’s why there’s no ring.
まさか…
You don’t mean …!
Assuming that is true,
でも仮にそうだとしたら
Aki-chan,
アキちゃん起きて
wake up!
あいつだけの問題じゃねぇかもな
he might not be the only problem.
どういうこと
What do you mean?
他の客も全員ルールに従っているとしたらどうだ
What if the other patrons are also obeying the rule …?
あの子たち　こっち見てる
Those kids are looking at us.
ニャー
ここってヤバイ店
This is a dangerous café.
かもな
Could be.
This place …
ここのことさ…
なんだよ
What about it?
Tell your dad?
おじさんに言う?
My old man has nothing to do with this!
親父は関係ねぇよ
何が?新入りさんだって?
What? You guys newbies?
I heard from Nagi-chan!
ナギちゃんから聞いたの
ナギちゃんってのはカウンターの彼女ね
Nagi-chan is the girl at the counter.
それでここ座っていい?
Anyway, can I sit here?
どうやって来たの?誰かの友達?
So, how did you find this place? Are you someone’s friend?
Uh no, we just stumbled across this place.
いや　来たばっかで
Oh I see. Been a long time since we had newcomers!
そうなんだ
でも新しい人久しぶり
Is that s—
そうなんだ
It’s always the same people here.
いつ来ても同じ人ばっか
The one reading a book is Setoro-san, right?
本読んでるのはセトロさんでしょう
On the second floor is Shimei-san and—
二階がシメイさんと…
Ah! Cute little Chie-chan!
可愛いチエちゃん
And over there are Kouji-kun and Rina-chan—aren’t they close?
であっちはコージ君とリナちゃん　仲いいの
And then there’s Nagi-chan, right?
それにナギちゃんでしょう　あとえーと
And who else …
The girl wearing a hat?
帽子かぶってる子
Ah, I’m Akiko. Nice to meet you!
アキコよろしく
リクオです
I’m Rikuo.
真崎
Masaki.
リクオ君と真崎君　覚えた
Rikuo-kun and Masaki-kun.
I’ve remembered it!
Ah! Say, um,
あのさ…えーと
have you seen a female android around?
女性型アンドロイド見なかった
One demerit point.
減点一
ルール違反
You broke the rule.
Oh. Sorry.
You don’t have to say it like that;
そんな言い方しなくてもいいんじゃない
すみません
まだ慣れてないんだから
he’s not used to it yet.
だって
But—
ルール違反はみんなが困るの
Infringing the rule troubles everyone!
ナギちゃん…
Nagi-chan.
はいい子なの
She’s really a good person.
この店のことすごく大事にしてるから
She cares about this place a lot.
Isn’t it just her job?
その割には仕事してねぇじゃん
またすねてる
Oh no, she’s sulking again.
ナギちゃん
Nagi-chan!
ヤバイ店って感じでもないか
I guess it doesn’t feel like a bad place.
つーかむしろ俺はこう言いたい
Rather, I’d like to ask:
なんでこんな店に来てんだ彼女
Why did she come to a place like this?
なんでって
“Why”?
俺分かった
I know.
ロボットと馴れ合いたくて来てんだろう　ドリ系ってやつだな
She wants to befriend robots.
She’s a dori-kei.
肩持つのか
You disagree?
いや　そういうことじゃなくて
Um. I don’t think it’s like that.
まぁ聞いてみりゃ分かるけどな
Well. You’d get it just by listening to her.
We’ll be told off again for breaking the rule.
また言われるよルール違反
そりゃ聞き方一つじゃねぇの
There’s more than one way of asking.
お　来た
Oh. Here she comes.
I brought them back!
取り返したよ
She says she’s sorry.
一応ごめんだって
いや　あの　僕も悪かったし
Uh, I was in the wrong too!
何照れてんだ
What’cha shy about?
その帽子似合う
That hat suits you.
でしょう　私もそう思うんだけどね
Doesn’t it? I think so too!
それでさ
So … ahem.
何
What is it?
まぁ店の外の話なんだけど
Well, it’s something about the world outside this café.
俺んちアンドロイドいねぇんだよ
There are no androids at my place.
Isn’t that uncommon in today’s world?
今時珍しいだろう
いるんだろう　アキコさんちは
You have them too, don’t you? At your place?
いるよ
Yep. We do. That’s why I’m here.
だからここに来てるの
どういうこと
What do you mean?
ここなら誰とでもお話しできるでしょう
Here, you can talk to anyone as you please, right?
いろんなこと分かるじゃない
So you get to know a lot of things.
何を
Like what?
相手の…気持ちかな
Such as … their feelings, maybe?
これは私んちの話ね
This has to do with my situation at home.
私は人間もアンドロイドもみんな家族だって思ってるのよ
I think of both humans and androids as my family.
でもねどんなに私と見た目がそっくりでも
But no matter how similar we appear to each other,
we’re totally different on the inside.
中身は全然違う
似てるけど全然違うのよね
We may look alike, but we’re totally different.
だからねよくこう思うの
So I often wonder,
“What do you think of me?”
あなたは私をどう思ってるのって
それがここにいる理由
That’s why I’m here.
I want to be able to speak with them
and understand more about them.
色々話してもっと分かってあげたいの
だって家族だから
Because we are family after all.
ああ　降ってきた
Bah. It’s pouring outside.
リクオとこんの来ないのか
Isn’t your android coming to get you?
「あいつらがなに考えてるか知りたい」って
I want to know what they’re thinking about.
どう思う
What do you think?
アキコさん関係
Regarding Akiko-san.
ああ　昨日の話
Ah, yesterday’s discussion.
彼女みたいなのもドリ系っていうのかな
Does someone like her count as a dori-kei?
俺は持ってないから分かんねぇけどさ
I don’t have any androids, so I wouldn’t know.
傘をお持ちしました マ…
Here’s your umbrella, Mas—
ああいう使い方するよりはいいんじゃねぇの
She’s way better than someone who uses them like that anyway.
物を大事にする人…なのかな
Could she be … someone who treasures things?
まぁいい人じゃね?
Well, she’s a nice person, right?
そうだよね
That’s true, isn’t it?
What are you relieved about?
なに安心してんだよ
いや　そんなんじゃないよ
No, it’s not like that.
まぁ確かに可愛かった
Well. She certainly was cute.
今日も行ってみっか
Should we go again today?
だから違うって
I said, it’s not like th—
Aki—
アキ…
お待たせして申し訳ありません マ…
I’m very sorry for making you wait, Mas—
かばん　防水　お前だけ帰宅
My bag. Waterproof it. Go on by yourself.
かしこまりました
Acknowledged.
コーヒーです
Here is your coffee.
やっぱりあの味
As I thought. It tastes like that coffee.
入れ方を変えております
I used a different brand.
Huh? I gave no such command!
そんな命令してないぞ
I thought Master would be pleased.
マスターが喜ばれるかと
なに勝手なことしてんだよ
Why did you decide that on your own?
お前まで人間の真似するのか
Are you trying to imitate humans too?
私はアンドロイドです
I am an android.
Not a human, Master.
人間ではありません　マスター
あなたは私をどう思ってるのって
“What do you think of me?”
見た目がそっくりでも
But no matter how similar we appear to each other,
Resembles
中身は全然違う
we are totally different on the inside.
逆か
The other way round?
We may look alike, but we’re totally different.
似てるけど全然違うのよね
Akiko’s Point of View
Resembles
もっと分かってあげたいの
I want to understand more about them.
だって家族だから
Because we are family after all.
ちょっと　ドリ系っぽいんだけど
Hey. You’re acting like a dori-kei.
ただ今戻りました
I have returned.
あれそうじゃない
Isn’t that it?
見覚えがある
Ah. I remember it.
やっと来た
It’s here at last!
お着替えをお持ちしました　マスター
I have brought your change of clothes, Master.
ありがとう
Thank you.
Huh? You thanked it?
お礼とか言ってんの
言わない?
I don’t know. Am I not supposed to?
No way.
言うわけないじゃん
Eh, she’s a dori-kei?
えーあれドリ系
何よそれ
What was that?!
だからあの店には行ってないって
I’m telling you. It said it didn’t go to that café.
命令以外のことしたか
Did you do anything aside from your orders?
しておりません
I did not.
あれはどうなんだよ　ほら携帯の
What about that?
The thing on your mobile phone.
行動記録?
The movement records?
それだ
Yeah, that.
Could it be a problem on this end?
こっちが間違ってるのかな
That’s why I say you trust robots too much.
だからお前ロボット信用しすぎだつーの
じゃサミィが嘘ついてるわけ
Then are you saying Sammy’s lying?
サ…
Sa—?
… Nothing.
いや…うちのアンドロイド
That’s our android.
So it’s called Sammy, huh?
サミィっていうのかあれ
だから別に信用してるわけじゃ
Well. It’s not that I’m really trusting it.
ロボット三原則言ってみろ
Why don’t you recite the three laws of robotics?
別に法学部じゃ
We’re not in law school.
いい加減覚えろよマスター
Stop arguing and just remember it already, Master.
えーと 一条
Um. Firstly,
人間に危害を加えない
Do not inflict harm upon humans.
First Law:    A robot may not injure a human being or, through inaction,
allow a human being to come to harm.
Three Laws of Robotics
おし
That’s right.
二条
Secondly,
一条に反しない限り
Obey commands from humans, unless this contravenes the first rule.
Second Law:    A robot must obey orders given to it by human beings,
except where such orders would conflict with the First Law.
Three Laws of Robotics
人間の命令に従う
覚えてんじゃん
Oh. You do remember after all.
三条…
Thirdly—
ってあったっけ
Was there a third?
自分の身を守る
Protect yourself.
Third Law:    A robot must protect its own existence, as long as such protection does not conflict with the First or Second Law.
Three Laws of Robotics
これがロボットの行動原理だ
These are the codes of conduct for a robot.
つまりそういうこった
In other words, that’s all there is to it.
どういうこった
What do you mean?
だから嘘をつくなって原則はねぇんだよ
That is to say,
there’s no law against lying.
First Law:    Do not inflict harm upon humans
Second Law:    Obey human commands
Third Law:    Protect self
嘘
No way!
案外知らねぇんだよなこれ
It’s surprising how you don’t know this.
まぁサミィちゃんの言うことは信用できないってこった
So, no matter what Sammy-chan says,
you can’t trust it fully.
午後はお買い物だったな
It goes shopping this afternoon, right?
な…なにが
What?
サミィちゃんだよ
I’m talking about Sammy-chan!
買い物するだけだって
Just shopping, it said.
それが本当かどうかは
There’s no choice but to confirm for ourselves if that is the truth.
直接確かめるしかねぇな
やっぱり行く
We’re going in after all?
んだよ確かめたくねぇのか
What is it now? Don’t you want to confirm it?
そういうわけじゃ…
That’s not it.
じゃいいだろう
Then that’s fine.
いいよ
Hm! All right.
なんだよそれ
What’s with that?
だから行くって
I said I’m going!
じゃ行こうぜ
Then let’s go.
Ah. Let’s go.
ああ　行こう
Ah. Welcome.
いらっしゃい
Hm?
どうしたの
What’s up?
安心すんのは早いな
It’s too early to be relieved.
これから来んのかもしんねぇぞ
It might come in later.
ここで待つの
We’re going to wait here?
とりあえず　晩飯まで粘るか
For now, shall we stick around until dinner?
ばったり出くわしたくないんだけど
But I don’t really want to confront it here.
Isn’t it all right here?
ここでいいんじゃね?
But I’m short-sighted.
僕ド近眼なんだよね
You can’t see it, even from here?
こっからでも見えねぇのかよ
After all, I can’t see anything if I take my glasses—
だって裸眼で0.1以下だし
ニャー
ニャー　ニャー
Chie-chan! Come down from there!
チエちゃん 下りておいで
猫なの
I’m a cat!
いや申し訳ない　お兄さん方
Oh. I’m so sorry, lads.
子供は自由に遊ぶのが一番　ですよね
It’s best for kids to play around freely.
Isn’t it?
Ah, freely.
ああ
自由だな
Come along. Give it up now.
ほら 止しなさいって
Those round things are weird.
あれが変なの
チエちゃん食べたいものがあるんだよね
Chie. There’s something you want to eat, isn’t there?
I am a cat!
猫なの
あんねアイス
And ice-cream!
If you don’t sit down, you won’t get to eat it.
椅子に座らないと食べられないよ
アイス　アイス
Heh. Sorry about that.
失礼
興味を持ったらほかの事はお構いなしでして
Once something catches her attention, she forgets all else.
ピアノだ
It’s a piano.
Are you going to play it?
弾くのか
I told you. I’ve quit playing.
だからもうやめたって
弾くのはね
I’ll play it.
あのおじさんと子供人間だよね
That old man and the kid are both human, right?
どう見ても人間だな
No matter how you look at them, they’re human. But you know—
つっても
なに
What?
アキコもここじゃ人間に見えたけどな
Akiko appears to be human here as well.
Huh?
私寂しい
How lonely.
僕だって寂しいよ
I will be lonely too.
Can’t we meet every day?
毎日はダメ?
うん　仕事もあるし
No. I have my job.
外で女の人と会ってるんでしょう
You are meeting other women outside, aren’t you?
いや そんなことないよ
No. That’s not it.
私を一人にしないでくださいね
Please don’t leave me by myself.
分かってる
Yes. I know.
場所　変えようか
Shall we go somewhere else?
What were you doing?
何してるのさっきから
Socializing.
交流を深めてます
Order something already.
注文してよ
Two blends.
ブレンド二つ
イヴレンド二つ
Evlends for two!
アイスだ
It’s ice cream!
はい　お待たせチエちゃん
Here. Sorry, Chie-chan.
A cat’s tongue can take the cold.
猫舌は　冷たいの平気なの
お前さ　怖いんだろう
You’re scared, aren’t you?
何が
Scared of what?
サミィちゃんが来るのが
Scared that Sammy-chan will come.
なに言ってんだよ
What are you on about?
That your robot is someplace unknown,
doing whatever it wants.
自分のロボットが知らないところで勝手なことをしてたらな
“Violating human authority!”
「人間の尊厳が侵されている」ってか
Is that it?
それおじさん
Your dad said that?
まぁ俺にゃ分かんねぇけどな
Well. I don’t know.
Don’t even have one.
持ってねぇし
なんで持ってないのさ
Why don’t you?
来た
Ah. You’re here.
I’m here!
来たよ
サミィが嘘つく理由が分かんない
I don’t get why Sammy would lie.
I find it harder to make sense of ring-less robots.
俺はリングなしのロボットの方が分かんねぇよ
ちょっと行ってくる
I’ll be right back.
リクオ君
Rikuo-kun!
What? What’s up?
なに　どうしたの
いやーもう
Eh? What?
全然違う
You’re completely different.
Heh? Really? I’m so happy!
そう　嬉しい
あ…あのさ
Uh, by the wa—
じゃなくて…質問
That’s not it. Question.
その…リングは　頭の上の
Where’s the ring on top of your head?
消してるよ
It’s off. If I don’t look human, it’ll be a rule violation.
人間と同じに見えないとルール違反だもん
But the robot laws—
でもロボット法
All right. This conversation ends here.
はい　この話終わり
Ah, Chie-chan!
チエちゃん
猫なの
I’m a cat.
どうしたのチエちゃん
Chie-chan. What’s up?
He’s wearing something weird.
変なの付けてる
変なのって
Something weird?
ニャー　ニャー
What do you want of me, Blade Runner?
私に何か　ブレードランナー
もっとうまく監視したらどうだ
Shouldn’t you do a better job of observing me?
男の纏わり付くような視線は
Having a man’s intense gaze on me …
is far from comfortable.
...気持ちのいいものじゃない
すみません
I’m sorry.
ルールに反抗的ではここは楽しまない
Violate the rules, and you won’t have fun here.
今日が賑やかですね
いや ここにいる意味がないらしい
No; rather, it would be meaningless to be here.
まぁ 受け売りだがね
That’s what I’ve been told.
持ってないもん
I don’t have it!
今日はいいの
Ah. Is today all right?
それでは 君のご友人によろしく
Well. Please give my regards to your friend.
あとで返してもらえると思うよ　多分
You’ll get them back eventually, probably.
多分
Probably?
She hid my hat before as well.
前に帽子隠されたことあったので
My glasses got taken.
メガネ取られた
ね　帽子は
So where was your hat?
帽子って
My hat?
隠されたって
She hid it right?
ああ　そうそう
Ah, that’s right. And then I asked where it was, and Chie-chan had it all along!
それでどこに隠したか問い詰めたらね　ずっとチーちゃんが持ってたの
また来てね
Please come again!
持ってたって
She had it?
パンツの中に挟んでた
She hid it inside her panties!
She must have taken a liking to it.
すっごく気に入ってたのにね
悪い　俺用事できた
Sorry. Something came up.
What a nice atmosphere, huh.
いい雰囲気じゃん
What’s up with Masaki-kun?
真崎君どうしたの
さぁ
Dunno.
今は開かないわよ
It won’t open now.
What?
誰か帰ったらしばらくロックされるの
When someone leaves,
it stays locked for some time.
なんでだよ
Why?
プライバシーって大切よ
Privacy is precious.
えーと
Um. Is this size all right?
このサイズでいいの
Yup.
うん
We have larger sizes.
もっと大きいのもあるけど
If it’s too big, the other household members will find out.
あんまり大きいと家の人に見つかるから
All right then. Hold on a second.
はいはい　ちょっと待ってて
I’ll get you a good blend.
いい豆入れてあげるから
どうしようか リナちゃん
What should we do, Rina-chan?
申し訳ございません　先にお通りください
I’m really sorry.
Please leave first.
はい　今日の分
Here. Today’s coffee.
Sorry for always taking things from your café.
いつもごめんねお店のもの
気に入ってくれた
Did they like it?
気に入って…くれてるのかな
I wonder if they did.
自分から聞くって手もあるわよ
You could always ask them yourself.
I can’t do that!
それはダメ
Why?
どうして
私から何かをするのが嫌いなの
He hates it when I try to start things.
勝手なことするなって
“Don’t do things on your own,” he’d say.
It’s all right.
大丈夫
He will definitely understand you.
きっと分かってくれる
だって　たかがローカルルールだろう
Well, isn’t this café’s rule a local one?
ロボット法とは比較にならないんじゃ
You can’t compare it with the robot laws.
またルール違反
You’re violating the rule again. You’ll get caught.
言いつけるよ
どうしてもダメ
You won’t say no matter what?
ナギちゃんには内緒にしてあげるから
I’ll keep it a secret from Nagi-chan, so this conversation ends here.
この話は終わり
内緒
Secret?
やっぱり内緒にできるんだ
So you really can keep secrets.
随分と変な話をしてますね
Quite a strange conversation you’re having.
誰にだって隠し事の一つや二つ
Everyone has a thing or two that they’re hiding.
Well, but she’s an—
いや だって彼女は…
In this café,
there is to be no discrimination
between humans and robots.
Ah, umm …
えーと
私もこの子に秘密にしていることがあります
I’m also keeping something from this girl.
嘘だってつかないわけじゃない
I’m not saying that I won’t lie to her either.
But it’s for this child’s sake.
でもそれはこの子のためです
アキコさんが内緒にするのも
Akiko-san is keeping that secret of yours …
リクオ君のためでしょう
for your sake too, isn’t it?
人間に危害を加えない
“Do not inflict harm upon humans.”
これがロボットの行動原理だ
“These are the codes of conduct for a robot.”
命令以外のことしたか
“Did you do anything besides your orders—”
しておりません
“I did not.”
僕が傷つくから
Because I will get hurt.
僕のため
… For my sake?
もっとも
To begin with,
メガネの在り処を言わなかったのは
she didn’t tell you where your glasses were because …
haha, she just wanted to play with you, isn’t it?
遊んでほしかったからでしょうが
パンツの中じゃ
They’re not in her panties?
誰かに渡したそうです
She seems to have handed it to someone.
Oh. It’s already this late.
もうこんな時間
帰るの
Are you heading back?
夕食の支度しないと
I have to prepare dinner.
これありがとう
Thanks for this.
あの…
Hey.
やっと気が付いた
Ah. You finally realized.
なんで黙ってたんですか
Why did you keep quiet about it?
You didn’t ask.
聞かれなかったから
客も店員も仲良しってわけですか
So the customers and staff here are chummy huh?
あれ
What?
くそ
Damn it!
Rikuo-kun.
リクオ君
なんだよ畜生
What’s this? Dammit!
リクオ君
Rikuo-kun.
勝手なことしやがって
… Doing things on her own!
あいつは俺の…
She’s my—!
座りなさい
Sit down!
はい
… Yes.
This cup’s on the house.
一杯くらいサービスしてあげる
That girl …
あの子
初めて来たのはいつだったかな
when did she first arrive?
最初は戸惑ってたんだけど
She was a bit confused at first,
だんだん打ち解けてきて
but she gradually warmed to us.
打ち解ける？
Warmed to you?
うん
Yup. She was able to talk to us about many things.
色々話してくれるようになったの
The mother who buys her clothes.
服を買ってくれるお母さん
Her occasional nightmares.
たまに見る怖い夢
ピアノを弾かなくなった男の子
The boy who would not play the piano any more.
それでこの間言ってきたの
Just the other day, she came in.
コーヒーをうまく入れたいって
Said she wanted to make good coffee.
色々と悩んでるみたい
She seems troubled by many things.
悩む
Troubled?
分からないのね
You don’t understand, do you?
自分のしていることが正しいのか
Whether the things one does are right,
間違っているのか
or wrong.
はい
Here.
ルールさえ守ってくれたら
As long as you are following the rule,
イヴの時間はいつでもご来店をお待ちしております
Time of Eve is always open to welcome you.
で結局そこで見失っちまった
So, in the end, I lost sight of him there.
外まで追いかけたの
You followed him outside?
あのロッポの頭の上を確かめたかったんだよ
I wanted to check if he had anything above his head.
あの店　ぜってぇなんかあるぞ
That café is definitely up to something—
Um.
あのさ
また　行ってみようと思うんだけど
I was thinking of going there again sometime.
Oh. I’ll come with you!
付き合うぜ
こうなったら徹底的に謎を暴いてやる
This time we’ll definitely unravel this mystery!
よし　じゃな
All right. See you then.
Say “hi” to Robot Sammy-chan for me.
ロボットサミィちゃんによろしくな
質問
Question.
なんでしょうか
What is it?
えーと
Um, that café …
あの店
マスター　申し訳あり…
Master, I am sorr—
Coffee.
コーヒー
かしこまりました
Acknowledged.
最近のコーヒー
Recently, the coffee’s …
おいしい…かも
been quite delicious, I think.
ありがとうございます
Thank you very much.
色々と面白いものが見られましてね
I saw a lot of interesting things.
まだ特定には至りませんが
But I haven’t pinned down anything specific.
倫理委員会とは無関係ね
Anything to do with the Ethics Committee?
だったらあんな下手な尾行はしないでしょう
If there were, they wouldn’t have used such a careless shadow.
しばらく泳がせて様子を見ます
I’ll let it swim free for a while, see where that takes us.
そうね
Indeed.
Chairwoman Ashimori.
芦森主任　現状において個性が定着しつつあります
As it is, it seems individuality is beginning to manifest.
これはもう抑制回路…
This means the suppression circuit is—
“Assumptions distract from the truth.”
先入観は真実を遠ざける
潮月ならそう言うはずよ
That’s what Shiotsuki would say.
続行します
I will continue my duties.
Love isn’t present there.
Ethics Committee
最近多くないこのCM
Hasn’t this commercial been appearing really often lately?
ステータス：リクオ
Status: Rikuo.
12:03 p.m.: Left the house.
午後12時3分より外出しております
昼食は外で取るそうです
Having lunch outside.
私が言うのもなんだけど
I’m just saying,
昼間からよく来るわね
but you come here really often in the afternoons, don’t you?
Hmm … Skipping classes?
サボリ?
Compensatory holiday.
振り替え休日
店員が言う言葉じゃねぇな
That’s not something a café assistant should say.
ごめん
Sorry. Rikuo-kun aside, I thought
Masaki-kun was a bit of a delinquent.
リクオ君はともかく
真崎君はちょっと悪い子だと思ってた
He’s on a scholarship. Quite unexpected.
特待生なんだよ　意外だろうけど
余計なこと言うなつーの
Don’t say anything unnecessary!
隠すことないのに
It’s not something to hide anyway.
おしゃべりする相手ならほかにもいるわよ
Hey. If you’re looking for someone to talk to, there are other people.
ああ二階はちょっと待って
Do you always carry that with you?
色々撮っておきたいんだ
Yeah. I take various pictures with it.
Well. We’ll get around to it eventually.
まぁそのうちな
Thanks for the meal.
ご馳走様
どういたしまして
You’re welcome. I’ll bring your after-meal Evlend over.
食後のイヴレンド持ってくるわね
イヴレンド　イヴレンド
Evlend. Evlend.
What?
なんだよ
違和感なくなってきた
I’ve stopped feeling uncomfortable about it!
Ah! Not my reading glasses!
老眼鏡はダメ
チエちゃん返してよ
Chie! Give it back!
猫なの
I’m a cat!
座ってるだけじゃ意味ないかもね
There’s no point just sitting around.
Well. I just want to know what this café is all about.
俺はこの店がなんなのか知りたいだけだ
I’ve no intention of getting close to any of the robots.
ロボットと馴れ合うつもりはねぇよ
アキコさん以外はまだ分かんないよ
We don’t know about anyone other than Akiko-san.
あれはどうだ　もっと右
What about them, to my right?
ドリ系が自分のアンドロイドを連れてきてる
A dori-kei getting intimate with his own android.
これ以上説明要らねぇよな
No further explanation needed.
どこ見てんだよ
Where are you staring?
お前さ
Come on.
見てないよ
I wasn’t staring!
見てたじゃん
No, you were—
見てないって
I’m saying I wasn’t!
いや見てた
You stared.
見てない
I wasn’t staring!
見てた
You were staring.
I wasn’t staring!
見てない
見てた
仲いいわね
You were staring!
You two sure get along well.
言われたことねぇ
そんなことないって
I’ve never been told that before!
No way!
男二人で盛り上がっても寂しいわよ
Just two boys getting all excited is pretty lonely you know.
今度変な目で見たら
The next time I catch you staring—
見てないって
I wasn’t staring!
何をだよ
At what?
コージ君が羨ましいんだ
So you’re jealous of Kouji-kun.
だから違うって
I’m not!
まぁ興味深いよな　だろう
He’s just very interesting, right?
ね
Hey!
こっち来ない
Why don’t you join us here?
暗い
怖い
Wouldn’t it be better not to do anything unnecessary?
余計なことはしない方がいいんじゃないか
余計かしら
Was it unnecessary, really?
自生に任せるのが筋と思うが
I think it would have made more sense to let things develop on their own.
Four people will stimulate more conversation, right?
四人のほうが話しも弾むんじゃない
彼はコージ　私はリナと申します
He’s Kouji. I’m Rina.
Ah, nice to meet you.
あ　どうも
俺真崎　こいつリクオ
I’m Masaki. This guy here is Rikuo.
Next time you stare, I’ll smack you.
次見たら手出すからな
I wasn’t staring!
見てないって
見てた
Was I?
Subconsciously huh?
無意識か
You two …
仲いい…
You two sure get along well.
仲いいんですね
そんなことないって
言われたことね…
No way!
Never heard that before!
こともないか
Or have I?
ニャー
よく来てますよねここ
Ah. You sure come here often.
はい
Yes.
Do you two come here together?
二人で一緒に来てんのか
いえ別々です
No. Separately.
弾んでいるな見事に
It sure is going splendidly, huh?
Ah, is that the Cinema Tide?
それってシネマタイド
May I have a look?　見せてもらっていい
Can I have a look?
お好きなんですか
Does he like it?
スイッチそこ
The switch is there.
What?
きれいだね
Ah, it’s beautiful.
Can you see a preview of it?
プリビューって見れるの
うん　そこの三角押して
Yes, if you press that triangle over there.
He’s just making conversation, isn’t he?
話題作りだろう
500積んでるから
It’s got 500.
そうだ
Oh. That’s right.
あの…
It has M-link, so maybe …
エムリンクだから多分
Um, hold on …
あの…ちょっと
やっぱりシネタいいな
Cine-Tide sure is awesome after all!
えーとじゃそんな感じで
Um. That’s about it, so …
外すときどうするんだ
How do I turn this off?
何これ
What is this?
これは違うんだよ
It’s not what you think.
Your heart … it’s so distant.
遠いんです　あなたの心が
何度会っても　寄り添っていても
No matter how many times we meet,
or how intimate we get,
不安で
I feel uneasy.
やっと理由が分かりました
I finally understand why.
私を一人にしないでくださいね
Please don’t leave me alone.
ドラマだな
That’s quite the drama.
僕のせい…かな
My fault … I guess?
It is your fault.
お前のせいだ
はいお待たせ
Sorry about the wait!
Wh-what?
な…なに
What is it?
何よ
なんとかしてきます
I’ll go take care of things.
どうしたの
What’s wrong?
まぁなんだ
Well. What do you call this? A scene of carnage?
修羅場?
R隊到着
Protected witness has arrived.
I was deployed as my Master’s guard.
私はマスターの護衛を実行しました
Then, Kouji is …?
じゃ　コージさんって
僕は今までなんてことを
What have I been doing until now?!
応急処置が不完全だったようです
It seems the emergency repairs were incomplete.
ここに来るのはコージ…その
You came here for Kouji’s, uh—
君のマスターの護衛ってこと
your Master’s protection?
いえ
No. I took my own initiative.
私自身の意思です
That leg; shouldn’t it be looked at by the maker?
それメーカー修理に出した方が
I cannot have anything to do with my legal maker.
私は正規のメーカーと関係を持つことができません
私のことがメーカーに知られれば
If my maker were to find out about me,
マスターが不利益を被るでしょう
my Master will be put in a disadvantageous position.
それよりも私は少しでも長くここにいたい
That aside, I would like to be here a little longer too.
Not even going for repairs.
修理もしないなんて
この店でもっとも人間らしく振舞えていないのは
In this café, I’m the one who acts least like a human.
Am I right?
私です　そうでしょう
私はいつ破壊されてもおかしくありません
I wouldn’t be surprised if I were destroyed sooner rather than later.
だから　使うことのない学習機能に自立的抵抗をかけているのだと思います
That is why I am autonomously resisting my useless learning functions.
Kouji treated someone like me …
コージは
こんな私を人間の女性として扱ってくれます
like a human female.
だから私はここで…幸せなんだと思います
I think that’s why I am happy here.
でも…
But, the woman in that photograph …
写真の女の人
You’re kind, aren’t you?
優しいんですね
でも大丈夫です
But it’ll be all right,
because I think Kouji’s kindness will not change.
コージの優しさは変わらないと思うから
やっぱり
I guess …
戻ります
I’m going back.
あのさ
Excuse me!
コーヒーが
The coffee—
When my coffee’s flavor changed,
コーヒーの味が変わってて
最初は怒ったんだけど
I was angry at first.
色々分かったら　少しだけ嬉しくなって
Then, after I understood various things, I was a little glad,
えーと
though she isn’t human …
相手は人間じゃないのに
Tell him!
言いなよ
Tell him what you want to say, even if he’s a human!
言いたいことは　相手が人間でも
なぜそう思うのですか
Why … do you think that?
知っているんですね　その時の気持ち
You knew, didn’t you, your feelings at that moment?
多分ね
Probably.
How did I end up saying such things?
こういうこと言うようになっちゃって
はい?
こっちが本命ってわけか
So you’re serious about this one?
さっきから気になってんだよ
Something’s been bothering me since just now.
お前とリナが一緒に映ってる写真が一枚もない
There is not a single picture of you with Rina.
撮るわけにはいかないよな
But I guess you couldn’t have such a thing.
恋人ごっこが外にバレたらまずいだろう
It would be bad if people knew you had an imaginary lover.
No; if this one is a robot too—
いや　案外こっちもロボットか
She’s not a robot!
ロボットじゃない
All the more reason then.
じゃなお更だ
What are you doing here?
ここで何してんだよ
恋人ごっこなんかじゃない
She’s not my imaginary lover!
じゃ本気だってのかよ
Then are you saying this relationship is for real?
愛情があるとか　吐かすんじゃねぇだろうな
“There is love.”
That’s not what you’re trying to say, is it?
君はこう言いたいんだ
What you’re trying to say is,
“For humans, a human partner is best.”
人間には人間のパートナーが一番だって
分かってんじゃんか
So you do understand that.
分かってる
I understand.
分かっている
I know that.
As you said, Rina and I cannot transcend a human–android relationship.
君の言うとおり　僕とリナは人間とアンドロイドの関係に過ぎない
分かり合えないことはあると思う
I think there are things we cannot understand about each other.
分かり合えるわけねぇだろう
There’s no way you could understand each other.
僕はね
You see.
マスターを助けたいんだ
I want to help my Master.
僕のマスター　リナとよく似ている
My Master is very much like Rina.
僕はマスターを助けたい
I want to help my Master.
昨日もいろんな人を見ました
Yesterday too; I saw a lot of people.
そんなの知らない
I don’t care about that.
しかしマスター
But, Master.
Master, you should look for a new partner.
マスターは新たなパートナーを見つけるべきです
A human—
人間の…
That’s enough. I’m tired.
もういいの
疲れた
コージがいい
You’re enough, Kouji.
あたしがロボットになるの
I’m going to become a robot.
So stay with me always.
ずっと傍にいて
マスターは僕に依存しきっている
My Master is morbidly dependent on me.
But I don’t know what to do about that.
でもどうすればいいのか分からなかった
リナと会ったとき
When I first met Rina, I thought she was just like my Master.
この人はマスターと一緒なんだと思った
僕に触れる仕草も　たまに見せる表情も
The way she behaves and touches me,
and the fleeting expressions she sometimes shows me.
I want to know more about Rina, to better understand my Master.
僕はリナのことをもっと知ってマスターを理解したい
マスターを助けたいんだ
I want to help my Master.
第一条だ
The First Law!
このことを　リナには黙っていてもらえませんか
About all this; can you keep it from Rina?
店のルールか
The café’s rule?
傷つけられないんです誰も
I don’t want to hurt anyone.
Convenient for you huh?
勝手だな
Aren’t you a failure?
ダメ人間じゃねぇか
みんなが幸せにはなれないんでしょうね
It seems no one can really attain happiness.
ありがとう
Thank you.
We should
get out of here.
それでは　失礼します
In that case, please excuse us.
いろんなのがいるよね
I guess there are all sorts.
Of humans?
人間が
Androids too.
アンドロイドも
叩いて悪かったな
Sorry about hitting you earlier.
Your eyes were right.
お前の目が正しかったわけだ
I should have taken a good look myself.
俺もじっくり見ときゃよかった
マサキ
Masaki.
目覚めたの
Have you awoken?
俺は思春期の中学生か
I’m not a pubescent junior high student!
でも リナの方は
But, Rina is—
No! It’s the other way round, isn’t it?
いや逆だろう
待てよ
Hold on.
What did Rina say, again?
リナはなんて言ったんだ
ここに来るのはコージ…その　君のマスターの護衛ってこと
You came here for Kouji’s, uh—
your Master’s protection?
いえ
No.
自分のマスターがコージとは一言も言ってねぇよな
She never once said her Master was Kouji.
Master
言ってない
She didn’t say it.
Master
店の外で　二人は無関係
They have nothing to do with each other outside of this café?
Master
でもどっちも相手が人間だって言ってる
But they both said the other is human.
Human
食い違ってる…
Something’s off—
Here you go! Thanks for waiting.
はいお待たせ
They might not have realized about each other.
気づいてないかもねお互いに
Yup. That’s it for hints.
はい　ヒントはここまで
Human
It’s the same!
同じだよ
Will you please explain this properly?
ちゃんと説明しろよ
Partners not knowing what the other is;
相手がどちらか分からないのは
アンドロイドも同じってこと
it’s the same with androids.
あの二人はお互いに興味を持ってて
They are interested in each other.
For different reasons, that is.
違う理由でな
お互いに隠してることもある
They also have things they hide from each other.
それはなんだよ
So what?
It’s like normal love.
普通の恋愛っぽい
いいこと言うじゃない
That should be a good thing, right?
でも　あんまり邪魔しちゃダメよ
But don’t interfere too much.
アンドロイド同士の恋愛
Love between androids …
疑似恋愛だろう
Pseudo-love huh?
それで先日の写真の女性
So that woman in the photo the other day.
どなたなんですか
Who was that?
えーと
アンドロイドが三角関係
A love triangle between androids.
説明が難しいな
It’s a bit hard to explain.
説明が難しい女性
A difficult-to-explain woman, huh?
アンドロイドの痴情のもつれ
Androids tangled in blind love.
変な突っ込み入れないでよ
Don’t think deviant thoughts!
You’ll tell me about it properly someday, right?
いつかはっきりさせますからね
いや…そうなの
I will?
お帰りなさいませ　マスター
Welcome home, Master.
Nao-chan and Mom have gone out for dinner.
Sammy-chan, please take care of the rest!!
What did you put on your head?
何頭につけてんだよ
お気に召しませんか
Do you not like it?
Vagrant Robot Reporting Hotline
Vagrant androids are dangerously likely to have corrupted thought logic. Report all discoveries immediately.
This is a request from the Ethics Committee.
倫理委員会からのお願いです
現在　倫理委員会では
Currently, the Ethics Committee …
マスターの管理下から外れて放置されている
is undertaking independent recovery of vagrant robots …
that have been removed from the supervision of their Masters …
浮浪ロボットの自主回収を進めております
これは何を描いたものですか
What is this drawing of?
自分のこと分からないの
You can’t recognise yourself?!
私…ですか
This is me?
そうだよ
That’s right! It is a drawing of ✲✲✲✲!
…の絵だよ
静かね
Isn’t it quiet?
つーか客いねぇし
You mean there are no customers.
Oh, but …
Huh?
あれ
帰ったのかな
Have they gone back?
本当に変な店だよな いろんな意味で
This really is a strange café, isn’t it?
In various ways.
あ…あのさえーと　ナギさんってなんでここで働いてるの
Ex-excuse me!
Nagi-san, why do you work here?
ナギでいいわよ
You can just call me Nagi.
Because I like it here.
ここが好きだから
I also like the people who come here.
ここに来る人もね
だから今日みたいに大好きなお客さんの顔が見えないのは寂しいわ
So on days like today, when I can’t see my favorite customers’ faces, I get lonely.
あの…僕らは
Um, what about us …?
Huh? What?
えっ　なに
This. Can I get a refill?
これ　お代わり
豆出してくるね
I’ll just bring out the beans. Please wait a while.
ちょっと待ってて
Enjoy your stay.
ゆっくりしてってね
It really is quiet, isn’t it?
本当静かだな
It’s an luh model.
LUH型だ
小学生くらいの時に出たハウスロイド
A houseroid model released when we were in primary school!
まだいたんだ
It’s still around, huh?
見たことねぇな
I’ve never seen one before.
あまり流行らなかったんだよ
They weren’t very popular back then.
使いにくいって苦情が多くて
There were many complaints that they were hard to use.
すっげぇ揺れてんだけど
It’s shaking pretty badly though.
店に用事?
Do you have some business here?
We’re just customers.
僕ら客なんだけど
Do you understand what a “customer” is?
客　分かる?
私も客です
I am also a “customer.”
おい
俺は真崎　こいつはリクオ
I am Masaki. This guy is Rikuo.
であんたは
So. Who are you?
Wh-what are you doing?
なに言ってんの
普通人間は自己紹介するもんだぜ
Normally, humans would introduce themselves.
自己紹介とは　私の名前をお伝えするということですか
Introduction is a process wherein I communicate my name, is it not?
This guy is trying to imitate humans.
人間のふりしてるつもりだぜこいつ
Heh. It’s abiding by the rule.
ルール守ってんだ
That’s right! It is a drawing of ✲✲✲✲!
そうだよ　…だよ
私は　「…」と申します
I am called … ✲✲✲✲.
なぜ耳を塞ぐのですか
Why did you cover your ears?
名前をお伝えしなければ　自己紹介は完了しません
If I do not communicate my name,
the introduction cannot be completed.
つまり私が人間であることを照明できません
In other words, I will be unable to verify my status as a human.
私の名前は「…」
My name is ✲✲✲✲.
It-it’s all right! You don’t have to overdo it.
いいんだよ　無理にしなくても
何をですか
Overdo what?
だから自己紹介
The introduction!
なぜですか　真崎様は先ほど
Why is that? Just a moment ago,
“Normally, humans would introduce themselves.”
「普通人間は自己紹介するもんだぜ」
とおっしゃいましたが
… is what you said.
マサキ
Masaki! This one cannot deal with fuzzy interactions!
こいつに曖昧な会話はダメだ
What should we do?!
どうすんだよ
とにかく自己紹介させないと
Anyway, if we don’t let it introduce itself—
あの音を
What about that sound?!
For the time being, we’ll have to bear with it.
とりあえず聞かなきゃ
We’re sorry! Go ahead and say it!
悪かった
じゃ言ってみろ
ですから　「…」です
Like I said, I am ✲✲✲✲.
い…いいお名前ですね
It-it’s a nice name huh.
私もそう思います
I think so too.
大切な名前です
It’s very important to me.
そりゃ結構
That’s wonderful.
Where do I find a restroom?
お手洗いはどちらでしょうか
でもあの壊れ方　あんなになるまでほっとかなくても
That broken machine,
it was left alone, to fall into such disrepair.
It should be returned to the maker for repairs—
メーカーに修理に出すとか
You’re talking like that again.
またそういう話してる
でも今日のはさすがに…
But I think today—
Rikuo-kun.
リクオ君
彼はお客
He is a customer.
You already understand that, don’t you?
もう分かってるでしょう
Everyone who comes here is the same.
ここに来る人はみんな同じ
Excuse me.
失礼します
Welcome. What would you like to order?
いらっしゃいませ
ご注文は
なんか変じゃね?
Something feels wrong.
It might not be able to decide.
判断できないのかも
This is something new for it after all.
初めてのことだろうし
あっち
Ouch!
注文　これもう一杯
Order! One more cup of this!
リクオ様と同様の注文をします
I would like to order what Rikuo-sama is having.
Yep. Two Evlends!
はい　イヴレツー
Going to drink the coffee?
飲めんのかコーヒー
Three cups might be pushing it.
三杯目はきついかも
No. I meant the robot.
いやロボットが
あの口はただのスピーカーだよ
That mouth is just a speaker.
人間の真似して飲んだら
What if it tries to drink, imitating humans?
そしたら
If it does that …
待てよおい
Hey. Hold on! The Third Law prohibits robot suicide!
Three Laws of Robotics
Third Law
A robot must protect its own existence, as long as such protection
does not conflict with the First or Second Law.
第三条　ロボットは自殺できない
飲んだらヤバイことくらい分かってんだろうこいつ
Does this guy not understand that drinking could be dangerous?
そうだよね
That is true. It wouldn’t try to drink … right?
飲むわけない…よね
どうかしましたか
Is something the matter?
コーヒーが
Coffee is … dangerous!
ヤバイ
な…なにやってるの
Wh-what are you doing?
なにって
What?
Thanks for waiting on the Evlend!
イヴレンド お待たせしました
な…なんで
Why?!
お客様がお飲みになるためでしょう
It’s for the customer to drink, isn’t it?
Don’t say such weird things.
変なこと言わないの
おい　ちょっと待って
Hey, hold it! wait!
Cut the switch!
スイッチ切れ
I haven’t done this before!
やったことないよ
命令だ
Or-order it! Just order it!
命令すりゃいいだろう
そうか
Oh. I see!
カップを下ろせ　命令だ
Drop the cup! It’s an order!
なぜですか
Why?
“Why”?
なぜって
あの方は
She said,
“It’s for the customer to drink, isn’t it?
「お客様がお飲みになるためでしょう」
「変なこと言わないの」
“Don’t say such weird things.”
とおっしゃいました
… a while ago.
私はお客です
I am a customer.
あっ　質問
Ah! Question!
なんでしょうか
What is it?
えーと
Um.
H-h-how old are you?
お…おいくつですか
Age-wise? This year I will be eight years old.
年齢のことですね
今年で八歳になります
多分八年前に作られたってこと
He probably means that he was manufactured eight years ago.
You thought I was a bit big to be an eight-year-old human, didn’t you?
八歳の人間にしては大きいと思いましたね
Not really—
いやんなこと…
No, Masaki-sama. It was written all over your face.
いえ　真崎様　そういう顔をしています
なんでここだけ細かいんだよ
Why’re you only concerned with this sort of detail?
しかしながら私は八歳
But I am eight years …
Eight years …
八歳
Eight …
八…
おい
論理とルールが矛盾してる
Its logic is in conflict with the rule. It cannot answer!
八…
答えられないんだ
どうすんだよ
What should we do?!
いや八歳って言っても色々ですから
Well! There are many types of eight-year-olds!
There are other eight-year-old humans who look like me, is that right?
八歳で私と同体型の人間が存在するということですか
そうそう
That’s right!
I do not have data about that.
私のデータにはありません
Please explain in detail.
詳しく教えてください
こ…この店によく来る人なんですよ
Th-th-th-there’s a frequent visitor to this café!
この店に来る方で八歳なんですね
Someone who comes to this café, and is eight years old?
What is this person’s name?
お名前は
チエちゃんって言って
Sh-she’s called Chie-chan! Well, she’s …
そりゃもう八歳…未満です
8 Years
Eight years old … not quite.
Not quite eight years
そうそう　でかいよな
That’s right! She’s big! Well, her voice is.
声とか…
The most important thing is that you believe me.
信じていただけて何よりです
What is your job?
仕事は何を
育児のお手伝いをしておりました
I helped with child care.
Ehh, child care huh?
育児ですか
はい
Yes. For a couple and their only son.
ご両親とご子息が…
Hey! Help me out here!
ちょっと　相手してよ
What?
なに
It’s tough doing this by myself, you know.
一人じゃきついんだけど
I am a customer.
私はお客です
Thanks for the coffee.
ご馳走様でした
給水タンク
A liquid-storage tank …!
What was all that hard work for?
今までの苦労はなんだったんだ
危機が去ったかな
The danger has passed, I guess?
失礼　ナギさんはどちらに
Excuse me. Where might Nagi-san be?
この子の昼寝の番をしてたら　私まで眠りこけてしまいました
While looking after her during her nap,
I fell asleep myself.
Something weird is sitting there!
変なの座ってる
そんなこと言っちゃダメだよ
It’s not nice to say such things.
Chie-chan, let’s go back?
チエちゃん　帰ろうね
猫なの
I’m a cat!
Umm.
あの…
Excuse me.
失礼
「チエちゃんって言って」
She’s called Chie-chan.
チエちゃんとは八歳未満の方ですか
Is Chie-chan the one who is not quite eight years old?
What?
この人チエちゃん
He, he is Chie-chan!
あなた何を言ってるんですか
What are you saying?
ニャー
こちら様は
This person is …
I’m a cat!
猫なの
こいつは猫だ
This one here is a cat!
これはこの子の口…
No, that’s just her favorite line—
もう猫でいいんだろう
Can’t we just call her a cat?!
本人が言ってるんだからいいの
She said it herself, so leave it!
はい
All right!
I. Am. A. Cat!
猫なの
おし　出口までご案内
Right! I will escort you to the exit!
Good-bye!
さようなら
Presently, the data is very complicated.
今　情報がかなり錯綜したのですが
おい　大丈…
Hey! Are you all ri—?
変なの落ちてた
The weird thing fell.
Um, is there any way I can help—
あの　何かお手伝いを…
頼むから　帰ってくれ
I’m begging you, please. Just go!
How is it? Can it be fixed?
どうだ　直るか
これもう…
It’s already—
Thank you, Rikuo-kun. But …
ありがとう　リクオ君
でも
After all that, let’s have a good chat.
せっかくだから　楽しくお話しましょう
じゃずっとその家で働いてたんだ
So, you’ve always been working at that house?
はい
Yes. That was where I worked.
そこが私の仕事場でした
私はご子息の世話係として雇われましたが
I was tasked with looking after the son.
今はもう私を必要としないほど成長されました
But now, he has grown to a stage where I’m no longer needed.
その仕事好きだった?
That job—did you like it?
はい
Yes.
ご子息が私に名前をくださったのを
The son bestowed a name upon me.
今でもよく覚えています
Even now, I remember it well.
大切な名前です
It’s an important name.
That child’s name! What was his name?
その子の名前　名前なんていうの
ご子息は
The son was …
「…」という名前です
His name was ✲✲✲✲.
家族の名字は?
What about the family name?
住所　連絡先は?
Their address? Contact details?
お前…
You were …
やっぱり…
As I thought.
I’m grateful that you asked about my name.
名前を聞いてくれて感謝します
“Everyone who comes here is the same.”
「ここに来る人はみんな同じ」
あなたが私を呼んだのですね
You called me,
didn’t you?
名前を…忘れ…ないで
… Name … don’t … forget it …
Yes! It is a drawing of Katoran!
そうだよ　カトランの絵だよ
Is it broken?
壊れたのか
It was illegally abandoned.
不法投棄されたんだ
は?
新しいの買ったら　古いのはメーカーに回収してもらうだろう
When a new android is purchased,
the old one should be returned to the maker.
その時に
At that time …
The collection fee.
回収費用
払いたくないから　個人情報を消去して
Because they didn’t want to pay it,
they erased their personal information.
この子はね　誰かに覚えていてもらいたかったんだ
This child, you see, wanted someone to remember him—
His own name.
自分の名前を
だから　倫理委員会から逃げ続けて
That’s why he has been evading the Ethics Committee.
You don’t know that.
分かんねぇだろう
It didn’t even know its own name.
名前なんて分かんなかっただろう
多分そこも消されて
That was likely erased as well.
ロボットらしいじゃねぇか
That’s just like a robot, isn’t it?
とっくに無くしてんのにそれに気づきもしねぇで
Not realizing that it had lost something ages ago.
この子の心の中にはずっとあったの
They remained in this child’s heart the whole time;
名前をもらったときの大切な思い出
those precious memories of receiving his name.
心?
Heart? What do you mean by “heart”?
心ってなんだよ
Masaki.
マサキ
You often said so yourself, didn’t you?
お前もよく言ってたじゃねぇか
「心がないから音楽も理解できない」って
“Because it doesn’t have a heart, it doesn’t understand music.”
いつまでも浸ってんじゃねぇよ
How long are you going to stay there blubbering?
いい加減にしろ
Stop it already!
What? Isn’t it strange?
んだよ
おかしいだろう
Right?
な
You too?
お前もかよ
Vagrant Robot
Report Form
So they also dispose of vagrant robots—
浮浪ロボットの処理もやってるんだ
The Ethics Committee.
倫理委員会って
俺がやってるわけじゃねぇよ
That doesn’t mean I was involved.
She’s really ignoring us huh.
やっぱり無視か
これが普通だろう
Isn’t that normal?
Sammy is like that at home too.
サミィも家じゃあんな感じ
Why is it different only at that café?
なんであの店だけ違うんだろう
思い入れなんて持つもんじゃねぇよ
Affection is not something they have.
This is me?
私…ですか
そうだよ　カトランの絵だよ
That’s right! It is a drawing of Katoran!
In a Time of Tenderness
次はこちら　蟠渓新聞一面です
Next up, the front page of Bankei News.
アンドロイドの業種拡大
Android job types expand!
It’s big news!
大きいですね
Where’s Sammy?
サミィは
It made that and went out a while ago.
とっくに出ていったそれ作って
あっ　メンテか
Maintenance?
月一とか面倒すぎ
So annoying. Once every month.
あれってどこ行ってんの　電気屋さん?
Where did it go?
An appliance shop?
さぁ　お父さんとこじゃないの
Who knows.
Probably Dad’s place.
眠い　食べたくない
I’m sleepy and don’t feel like eating.
Android job types expand.
Androids employed as school teachers?
Birth of android artists?
ピアノ
The piano.
What?
はい?
夜中に弾くなら音消してよ
If you’re gonna play at night, turn off the sound!
I’m losing sleep because of it.
こっちまで寝不足だわ
So it wasn’t a dream.
あれ…夢じゃない
お母さん嘆いてたよ
Mom was heartbroken!
Gone for voice training
lessons. Sammy-chan,
take care of breakfast.
—Mom
レッスンもう手伝ってもらえないって
Says she can’t have you help with the lessons.
僕がうまくなってもしょうがないじゃん
Even if I were good at it, what’s the use?
Hayama Junior Piano Competition
Robot gives guest performance.
Grand Prix – Sakisaka Rikuo (14 years old)
なんかこいつ特技とかねぇのかな
It doesn’t have any special abilities?
アンドロイドに特技とか
Special abilities in an android?
親父のPCん中で見つけた
I found this on my old man’s pc.
Uh …
えーと
アンドロイドだ
It’s an android.
人間の親になるためのな
Made to be a human being’s father.
I’ve heard about it—
こんなの聞いたこと…
They’re not actually in use.
実際に出回ってるわけじゃねぇ
将来的には実現したいって話だ
They might be, in future.
Read this.
ここを読んでみろ
… Operational tests conducted in secret …
心当たりあるよな
Sounds familiar?
Not particularly.
別に
It doesn’t mean he’s like that.
あの人がそうと決まったわけじゃ
It’s like robots are butting into everything.
ったく 何でもかんでもロボットが割り込んできやがって
First it’s art. Next it’ll be love!
芸術の次は愛情だな
マサキ
Masaki!
Would you eat a tomato created by machines?
いらっしゃい
Welcome!
You’re alone today?
今日は一人?
Not like we’re always together.
別にいつも一緒じゃ
You are!
一緒でしょう
そっちも一人?
She’s alone too?
うん
シメイさん　ちょっと用事で
Shimei-san has something to take care of.
託児所もやってるんだ
So you handle child care too?
チエちゃんはお客様
Chie-chan is a customer!
ね?
Right?
ニャー
What’s he up to?
何してるの　チエちゃん一人にして
Leaving Chie-chan on her own.
I’m a cat!
猫だもん
もうそんなこと言わないの
Don’t say things like that!
はいはい
Sure, sure.
Hopefully your dad will be back soon.
お父さん早く帰ってくるといいね
He’s not my dad!
お父さんじゃないもん
じゃ何
So who is he?
He’s called my … fos-ter-par-ent!
養育…里親っていうの
戻ってきたよ　チエちゃん
I’m back, Chie-chan!
猫なの
I’m a cat!
Oh. Rikuo-kun!
ああ　リクオ君
Huh? Where’s Masa-kun?
あれ　マサキ君は
It’s not like we’re always together!
だからいつも一緒じゃ
Sure you are!
一緒でしょう
なんか元気ないね
You seem kind of out of it.
Out of it, nyaa.
元気ないニャー
You’re wrong!
んなことないって
Chie-chan. Let’s read a book!
チエちゃん　ご本読もうか
I don’t feel like it.
いいもん読まなくて
シメイお爺ちゃんが好きな本知ってる
You know which book Shimei-ojiichan likes?
How about I show you?
教えてあげようか
ニャー
She’s good with kids.
うまいんだ子供の相手
That’s because she’s mature.
大人だからねアキコは
Unlike me.
私と違って
シメイさんって何してる人
What does Shimei-san do for a living?
私も知らないの
I’m not sure what he does either.
Except for doting on Chie-chan.
チエちゃんを溺愛してる以外はね
一緒に連れていけばいいのに
He should have taken her with him.
多分　つらいのはシメイさんのほう
Probably.
But Shimei-san’s the one who is suffering.
I kind of understand.
なんとなく分かるの
もう何度も預かってるから
I’ve taken care of her many times.
何度も？
Many times?
うん
Right. Every month.
毎月ね
Cats study too!
猫も勉強するもん
Are you okay?
大丈夫
ちょっと寝不足
I didn’t get enough sleep.
そうじゃなくて
That’s not what I mean.
Seems like you’re in a bad mood.
なんか不機嫌そう
どうせ僕は嫌な奴だよ
What does it matter?
You all hate me anyway!
何よそれ
What do you mean by that?
生まれたばっかりだと　心の中は何にもないんだって
They say there’s nothing in your heart at birth.
空っぽ
It’s empty.
Cats too?
猫も?
うん　でもねいろんな人と話して
That’s right. But you talk with lots of people,
いろんなものを見て感じてそうすると
and feel and see lots of things,
だんだん心ができてくるんだって
and gradually your heart comes into being.
Cats too?
猫にも
そうだよ　でもまだまだ
That’s right, but you’re still a child.
これからもっといろんな心ができてくるんだって
You’re going to experience many more emotions.
ニャー
Not just Chie-chan.
チエちゃんだけじゃなくて
Shimei-san, us, and also—
シメイさんも　僕たちも　それから
リクオさん
Rikuo-san?
猫分かったよ
This cat understands.
本当
Really?!
ニャー
Chie-chan understood before I did!
チエちゃんに先を越されちゃった
Are you lonely without Shimei-san?
シメイさんがいないと寂しい?
Do you like Shimei-san?
シメイさんのこと好き?
ニャー
シメイさんって　一人でどこかに行っちゃうんだよね
Shimei-san went off somewhere, all on his own.
I wonder where he goes,
どこ行ってるんだろうね　寂しがってるのに
and whether he’s lonely …
リクオ君
Rikuo-kun!
She’s just a child, you know?
大人気ないんだから
ごめん
あのね　トイレ
Um. Sorry.
Bathroom.
はい　今度はチエちゃんの番ね
It’s Chie-chan’s turn now!
リクオ君ちょっとごめんね
Rikuo-kun, excuse us a second.
うん
Sure.
本当は一人で行けるのに
I can do it by myself.
さすがチエちゃん
That’s my Chie-chan!
シメイ氏がこの店に初めてあの子を連れてきてから　もうかなりなる
Shimei-shi first brought her to this café quite some time ago.
あのご老人が言うには
According to that elderly gentleman,
ここは彼女のお気に入りなんだそうだ
she really likes it here.
I didn’t mean to weigh her down.
いじめるつもりはなかったんです
でも　ちょっと気になることが…
But something bothers—
It can’t be helped.
なに仕方ないさ
人間誰だって相手を傷つけることはある
All human beings hurt their companions sometimes.
どういう意味ですか
What are you getting at?
I guess that got you angry.
気に障ったかな
僕が人間だから　嫌なやつだってことですか
You’re saying I’m a bad guy because I’m a human?
面白いことを言うな君は
You say some interesting things.
ロボットなら絶対に相手を傷つけないとでも
Do you think robots never hurt others?
何が相手を傷つけるのか
What is it that hurts others?
そう簡単に分かることじゃない
It’s not such an easy thing to figure out.
What were your thoughts at that time?
その時どう考える
どうすれば傷つけずに済むか
How can you avoid hurting others?
何を理解すればいいのか
What do you need to understand?
言葉にすれば
It’s easy enough to say,
身も蓋もない話だな
but quite another thing to put into action.
Rikuo-san!
リクオさん
私はリクオさんに救われました
You saved me.
Is that so?
そうなんだ
Ughh, this sucks.
最悪だ
じゃ司法関係に進むんだ
So you’re going into administrative justice.
Seems not many lawyers specialize in robot law.
ロボット法の専門弁護士ってまだ少ないらしいし
まぁ狭き門には変わりねぇけどさ
But it’s still tough to get into.
What about you?
お前は
This, after all?
やっぱこれか
I’m quitting.
もうやめる
なんでだよ
Why?
やっぱあれかこの間の
Because of that, the other day?
うん
Forget about that.
別に気にすることはねぇって
そりゃ 正確には弾けんだろうけど
Sure, it can play with precision.
But it only stole a bit of the spotlight.
すごく…うまかった
It was really … good.
感動したかも
I was moved, I think.
By this?
これにか
Huh?
あれ
下手だな
It’s lousy.
Ah. That’s right!
そうか
I’m sorry.
ごめんなさい
弾けるって言ったのは嘘
I lied when I said I could play.
But you made it to the end, right?
一応最後まで弾けたのかな
本当は見様見真似なんです
Really. I just picked it up by watching.
I’d just heard it so many times. That’s all.
前に何度か聞いたことがあるだけで
チエちゃんがもっと聞きたいって
Play some more, play, play! Nyaa!
もっと弾いて
弾いて弾いて
ニャー
Chie-chan, what did you like best?
チエちゃんどんなところが気に入ったの
猫はね
When it was … all broken up!
えーとバラバラのとこ
バラバラ
バラバラですね
ねあれ見て
Look at that! Isn’t it amazing?
すごくない
Hey, Rikuo-kun.
ねリクオ君
これ　ありがとう
Thanks for this.
That’s not what you were playing before!
さっきのとは違うよ
Ma—
マ…
リクオさん
Rikuo-san!
あの…私
Um, I’m …
That piece you used to play;
昔リクオさんが弾いてたのを
I liked it.
その…好きで
そしたらチエちゃんが聞きたいって
And Chie-chan said she wanted to hear it.
でも　ちゃんと弾いたことなくて
But I’ve never really played it.
それでも　楽しそうに聞いてくれるから
But she still enjoyed listening to it.
I’m sorry for having been so inconsiderate.
勝手なことして　ごめんなさい
I tried not to play in front of you.
お前の前では弾かないようにしてた
気が付いたら弾かなくなってた
And before I knew it, I’d stopped playing.
お前までピアノうまくなったら嫌だし
I’d have hated it if even you could play well.
リクオさん
Rikuo-san.
でも
But …
そんなのどうでもいいか
… To hell with all that!
ニャー　ニャー　ニャー　ニャー
I want to hear more!
チエもっと聞きたい
Sammy might play for you!
サミィちゃんが弾いてくれるかもよ
ニャー
いや嬉しい
I’m so glad.
She hasn’t been that happy for a long time.
あの子があんなに喜んだのは本当に久しぶりです
It was no big deal.
僕は別に
As for me,
それに引き換え
I left her on her own again.
私はまたあの子を一人にしてしまいました
You can’t take her with you?
連れていけないんですか
まだあの子には見せたくないんです
I don’t want to show her yet.
シメイさん　もしかしてあなたは
Shimei, could it be that you’re—?
I am needed by her.
私はあの子に必要とされています
So I devote myself to her.
だから私はあの子のために尽くします
She is everything to me.
あの子は私のすべて
My only wish is to make her happy.
私の願いはただあの子を幸せにすることなんです
あなたの演奏のように
Just like your performance.
That’s why I was so happy.
だから嬉しかった
These feelings are genuine.
この気持ちは本物ですよ
あなたの演奏に感動した私に誓って
I was truly moved by your performance, I swear.
言っていいんですかそんなこと
Is it okay to say that kind of thing?
ナギさんには内緒です
Just don’t tell Nagi-san.
サミィちゃん見なかった?
Have you seen Sammy-chan?
Come to think of it,
そう言えば　私が来たときに入れ違いで出ていったような気がしますが
I think she left when I came in.
帰っちゃったんだ…
She left …
お疲れ様
For your hard work.
About Sammy;
サミィって
What?
なに
She makes a lot of friends.
いろんな関係作ってるんだなって
I-It’s not l-like I’m angry!
別に怒ってないよ
格好良かった
You were really cool.
This café—
この店
I … don’t hate it.
僕
嫌いじゃないよ
I … don’t hate it.
Thank you.
ありがとう
リクオ君
Rikuo-kun!
Right. I’ll explain it at the next meeting.
そうだ
その件は次の報告会で説明するつもりだ
I’m home.
ただいま
Anyway, take a look at the records.
とにかく　調書に目を通してくれ
Regardless of what the upper echelon say,
上の連中がなんと言おうと
this is the best way to study them all.
すべての会所を簡易調査するには　この方法がベストなはずだ
お父さんは
Where’s Dad?
家庭裁判所に出かけています
He went to the Family Court.
予定では　そろそろご帰宅されるはずです
He is expected to be home shortly.
絶対　お母さん悪くないよ
There’s no way Mom did anything wrong.
そうですね
That’s true.
でも　お父さんだけを責めてはいけませんよ
But you can’t just blame Dad.
Because neither side is clearly wrong.
どちらか一方が完全に悪いわけではないのですから
でも
But …
私からのお願いです
I have a favor to ask of you.
Sure!
はい
Let’s not tell Dad about this conversation.
この話はお父さんには内緒にしましょう
なんで
Why?
お父さんが傷つくからです
Because it would hurt Dad.
それは嫌でしょう
You don’t want that, right?
So I ask this favor of you.
では　私からのお願いです
Sure!
はい
困ったよ　マサカズ
Masakazu, there’s a problem.
壊れてしまったのかな
I think it’s broken.
Good morning, Tex.
おはよう　テックス
テックス
Tex.
Hey, Tex!
ね テックス
Tex!
テックス　テックス
Next, the report from the preliminary investigation.
続いて　事前調査の結果報告です
This shows the places that seem to be inciting excessive human–robot interactions.
アンドロイドと人間の過度な関係を誘発していると思われる施設の所在地を表示します
多すぎるな
There’re too many.
1408 places.
1408ヶ所です
あらゆる情報を収集し　すべてデータ化しました
We gathered all possible information and digitized it,
根拠のない噂話や都市伝説程度のものも含まれていると思われます
Baseless rumors and urban legends were included as well.
もう少し絞るべきだな
We need to narrow it down.
Time of Eve
残念なことに　これらの施設がはっきりとロボット法に抵触しているとは限りません
Unfortunately, not all these places clearly violate robot law.
グレーゾーンです
They’re in the grey zone.
That so many such places exist shows the limitations of robot law as it stands now.
そして対象がこれだけの数に上るという事実が
今のロボット法の限界でもあります
だが　消し去るべき場所だ
But these places must be eliminated.
We’ll do a cursory inspection of all the places,
これらの施設すべてに簡易調査を行い
その結果次第で本調査の対象へと格上げします
and then pick targets for full investigation.
メディアで吊るし上げるのはそれからです
After that, hand them over to the media.
But it’s impossible given the sheer number!
だからこの数では到底不可能だと言ってるんだ
人材という観点から考えればそうですが
That’s true, if you look at it only in terms of our manpower.
For the first time ever, we’ll use androids in the cursory investigation.
今回は初めて
簡易調査にアンドロイドを使用します
We’ve already secured a large number.
すでに相当数の機体を確保
We’re getting them ready now.
ただいま準備中です
ロボットアレルギーの君らしくないじゃないか
What happened to your robot allergy?
毒を以て毒を制す
We’re fighting poison with poison.
と考えていただければよろしいかと
Please think of it that way.
Continue.
続きを
はい
We’ll only investigate the places fully if accusations are supported by the android investigations.
このアンドロイドを使用した簡易調査で　裏づけが取れた案件のみを本調査リストに加えます
更に その際現場で目撃した人間　アンドロイドすべてを記録
We’ll also record all androids and humans seen at each place, and follow up with more investigations.
追跡調査を実施します　悪質な場合は　即座に警察当局内部のメンバーに通報　検挙を促します
Suspects will be reported to committee members in the police force, who will be urged to make arrests.
How are things with the apc?
APCの動向は
We were informed that someone found out about our preliminary investigations.
事前調査を嗅ぎまわっていた人物がいるとの情報が入っています
Their relationship with the apc is unclear.
APCとの関係性は不明
また　ロビー活動はこのところ沈静化している模様です
Also, lobbying has been diminishing.
聞いての通り　この調査に託けて
Don’t forget that some parties will try to trip us up using this investigation.
揚げ足を取ろうとする連中がいることを忘れないでいただきたい
アンドロイド調査員には
We will issue absolute orders to the android investigators;
they must keep their ties with our committee a secret.
本調査と倫理委員会の関係を極秘事項にするよう絶対命令を徹底します
あの傷害事件の記憶が風化している今
Memories of that incident are fading.
同じ過ちは決して犯してはならん
We must not make the same mistake again.
続けてくれ
Carry on.
メディア戦略部です
I’m from the media strategy division.
About cio Masaki’s tv appearance—
真崎CIOのテレビ出演が一件
うちの家内が欠かさずアーカイブしててな
My wife records them all.
敵わんよ
Drives me nuts!
これは強調しておきますが
I’d like to emphasize that our Ethics Committee is raising the alarm about robots infiltrating daily life. That’s all.
われわれ倫理委員会が警鐘を鳴らしているのは　あくまで日常生活の場に進出するロボットの存在です
Woah! What a lady-killer!
おお　マダムキラーって感じ
Huh? In what way?
えっどの辺
Hey! You changed the channel!
ああ　勝手に弄ってる
Don’t mind it!
お邪魔してます
Children treat robots like people no matter how primitive the robots are.
primitive they are.　特に子供は それが原始的な造形のロボットであっても　擬人化してしまえるんですよ
それによって本来あるべきはずの人間同士の関係性が阻害される
And that impedes the fostering of inter-personal relationships humans should have.
One Evlend!
イヴレンド
It’s an encroachment on human dignity.
人間の尊厳が侵されている
Sure.
はい
The issue I’m raising here is—
ここで問題にしたいのは
Hey, why doesn’t Masaki-kun come anymore?
ねね　最近来ないね真崎君　なんで
Actually, a lot has happened.
実は色々あって
A lot?!
色々って
まぁ一番の原因は
Well. The biggest reason is …
This guy is on tv a lot these days, huh?
最近この顔よく見ない
まぁね
Yeah. Like the old days.
昔みたい
何それ
What was that?
The parent organization of the Robot Ethics Committee …
倫理委員会の母体となる組織は　ロボットが一般家庭に普及し始めた当初から存在していた
has been around since androids started being used in households.
That’s more than ten years ago.
もう十年以上前か
I heard that it started out as a radical anti-robot organization.
当時はかなり過激なロボット排斥団体だったと聞いている
全然知らなかった
I had no idea.
ここ数年鳴りを潜めていたからな
They’ve been quiet for the past few years.
どういうことですか
What do you mean?
昔　その過激さゆえに傷害事件を起こしたことがあってね
Their extremism led to an incident.
The Tokisaka Incident, right?
それって　トキサカ事件のことですよね
聞いたことあります
I’ve heard of it.
Ah. They say it was an accident.
まぁ事故とも言われているが
いずれにせよ　世間からの非難は必至　責任取って当時の会長は辞任
At any rate, they were severely censured, and the head resigned.
それ以来少なくとも最近までは大人しかった　というわけだ
Since then, they’ve been quiet, at least until recently.
You’ve lost me.
難しい話
それが真崎君と関係あんの
Does it have anything to do with Masaki-kun?
…そう考えております
… that is our stance.
真崎様　ありがとうございました
Thank you very much.
Today’s guest for Zoom-in
Scramble was Masaki Atsuro,
本日のズームインスクランブルはゲストに倫理委員会広報官
真崎篤郎様をお迎えし　お話し伺いました
Chief Information Officer of the Ethics Committee.
Masaki.
真崎
うん　家庭の事情かな
That’s right. His family circumstances …
今日も誘ったんだけど
I invited him today, too—
真崎って名字だったの
So Masaki is his last name.
You’re hung up on that?
そっちですか
Not that!
そっちじゃない
Father’s orders?
Speakers could be broken!!!
So, how’s it going?
よ　元気か
There’s this café called Time of Eve.
イヴの時間って店があってさ
リクオがご執心なんだよ
Rikuo’s a big fan.
まぁ俺も行ってるから　人のこと言えねぇけどさ
Well. I go there too, so who am I to talk?
人間とアンドロイドが普通に話すんだぜ
Humans and androids talk to each other!
It’s totally absurd.
バカみたいなとこだろう
なぁ
Right?
なんか言えよ
Say something.
I’m coming in.
入るぞ
Who’re you talking to?
誰と話してるんだ
携帯
My mobile phone.
I hung up already.
もう切った
コーヒーを入れさせたのか
You had it make coffee?
うん
最近家にいることが多いじゃないか
You’re at home a lot these days.
何かあったのか
Did something happen?
何でも父さんに言いなさい
You can tell me anything.
There’s nothing.
いや 別にないけど
そうか
I see.
口に入れるものはあまりロボット任せにするなよ
Don’t trust robots too much when it comes to things you eat and drink.
THX 今夜中に今日の報告会の議事録を作成しろ
Thx. We’ll write up the minutes for today’s meeting tonight.
データは私の端末の中だ
The data is in my terminal.
Tell Masaki-kun he’s welcome any time.
いつでも来てって言ってね真崎君に
Sure, I’ll tell him.
うん　言っとく
But don’t get your hopes up.
あんまり期待しないでほしいけど
それじゃ
See you.
バイバイ
Come again!
また来てね
あの　帰りましたけど
Um. He’s gone.
ねぇ　リクオ君も気にしてないと思うけど
You know, I don’t think Rikuo-kun minds anymore.
私はそんな感じするよ
That’s the impression I get.
ナギさんはリクオのこと分かってないの
Nagi-san, you don’t understand Rikuo.
I’ve known him longer.
私の方が付き合い長いんだから
I’m sure he doesn’t want to see me here yet.
きっとまだ顔を合わせたくないって思ってる
そう?
Really?
Hey, who cares about Rikuo-kun?
ねぇ　リクオ君のことはどうでもいいんだけどさ
どうでもいいことないでしょう
そういう言い方しないでよ
Don’t say that!
I can’t just ignore him!
Oh? So that’s how it is.
そうなんだ
Don’t go telling Rikuo-kun strange things.
リクオ君に変なこと吹き込まないでね
バイバイ
真崎君　告げ口したりしないよね
Masaki-kun’s not going to report this place, is he?
ニャー
その時は　クローズするしかないわねこの店
If that happens, this café will have to close.
そんな　素敵な場所なのに
No! … Even though it’s such a wonderful place?
サミィちゃん
Sammy-chan.
最初にどうやってここに来たのか覚えてる
Do you remember how you first came here?
I thought you called me.
ナギさんが呼んでくれたのかと思った
I’m not able to bring anyone here.
私には誰も連れてくることなんてできない
You probably learned about Time
of
Eve from someone who’d been here.
あなたにイヴの時間を教えたのは　多分ここに来たことのある誰か
And Sammy-chan, you brought Rikuo-kun and Masaki-kun.
そして そんなサミィちゃんがリクオ君と真崎君を連れてきた
だからね　真崎君が連れてくるのが倫理委員会の人なら　それはそれで仕方のないこと
So if Masaki-kun brings someone from the Ethics Committee,
there’s nothing we can do about it.
That’s the end of these connections.
この繋がりはそこでお仕舞い
And the end of this café.
この店もお仕舞い
ナギさんはそれでいいの
Nagi-san, are you okay with that?
ここはね　みんなの心一つで成り立つお店
In this café, everyone’s hearts come together as one.
私は見届けたいだけ
I just want to see it through.
この輪がどこまで広がっていけるのか
How big can this circle grow?
Um. Master.
あの　マスター
Wh-what?
な…なに
真崎様にまた来てほしいですか
Would you like Masaki-sama to come again?
イヴの時間に
To Time of Eve.
Yes. I’d like him to come again.
うん　来てほしいと思ってる
I would like that too.
私もそう思います
Okay! I’ll definitely bring him tomorrow!
よし　明日こそ絶対に連れていくぞ
Masaki!
マサキ
今日は…
Today—
I’m not going.
行かねぇよ
また来てほしいって言ってたよ
She said she wants you to come again.
Don’t just say things.
適当なこと言うな
本当だって
It’s true!
Who?
誰がだよ
えーとナギさんとか
Nagi-san, and—
Sammy said so too!
あっ サミィも言ってた
あいつも来てほしいって
She said she wants you to come too.
They want me to come?
来てほしいって
So what? It’s a houseroid!
なんだよ
ハウスロイドだぜ
うん
That’s right.
そうだよ
お前
You’ve … changed.
変わったよな
Masaki, what’s going on?
マサキ
ね　なんだよ
あの頃の俺と同じじゃねぇのか
You’re just like I was, back then.
愛情を感じたって　いつか裏切られる
You’ll feel affection, only to be betrayed later.
あんな店ない方がいいだろう
It’d be better if that café didn’t exist.
そうだ
That’s right. It’d be better if it didn’t exist.
ない方がいい
Dad! I want to talk to you about something!
親父　話があるんだ
Thx is gone.
THXがいなくなった
マサカズ　何か命令したのか
Masakazu, did you give it an order?
No.
いや
勝手にいなくなるなんて
It just went off.
It’s completely broken.
完全にいかれたか
速いところ見つけて処分しないとな
Gotta find it right away, and get rid of it.
処分
Get rid of it?
当たり前だ
Of course!
あれは倫理委員会の資料にも散々触れているんだぞ
It’s handled lots of Ethics Committee material.
面倒なことになる前になんとかするんだ
Gotta take care of it before it becomes a headache!
Masaki. I’m at Time of Eve. Can you help me?
マサキ　今はイヴの時間なんだけど
ちょっと助けてくれない
What’s that sound?
なんだよこの音
やたら旧式のロボット…あっ
An ancient robot—uh, an elderly customer—is here.
古い感じのお客が来てるんだけど
It says to close the café!
この店を閉鎖しろって
I’m asking, what is that sound?
だから音はなんだって
The screen …
これは…
とにかく何言っても止めないんだ
Anyway, it won’t stop, whatever we say!
And this thx model won’t talk.
それにこのTHX型全然しゃべらないし
おい　なんだって
Hey—what did you just say?
This café falls under the grey zone, right?
この店ってグレーゾーンなんでしょう
こっちに来てお得意のロボット法でなんとかしてくれないかな　なんて
Do something with those robot laws of yours, please?
That was fast!
速っ
Close this establishment immediately.
Tex, stop it.
テックス　止めろ
T-Tex?
テ…テックス
What are you doing here?
お前なんでここに
Oh, so that’s what this is about?
そういうことか
You bring someone’s robot, and you want to make a scene, huh?
人んちのロボットを勝手に連れてきて　三文芝居でも見せようってかお前らは
どうやって連れてきたのか知らねぇけどさ
I don’t know how you brought it here,
but you people got Rikuo’s robot to come here.
まぁあれだろう　リクオのロボットも連れてきたくらいだ
色々とできんだろう
You can do all kinds of things.
この不思議なお店はよ
This is a strange place, after all.
Nagi-chan didn’t bring it here.
べ…別にナギちゃんが連れてきたんじゃ
アキちゃん
Aki-chan.
そこまでして俺を引っ張り出したいわけだ
You’ll go that far to get me to come here.
I’ll tell you my story.
教えてやるよ
昔こいつに育てられた
It raised me, long ago.
It was my best friend.
誰よりも仲がよかったな
ある時こいつは突然しゃべらなくなった
Then one day, it suddenly stopped talking.
ガキだった俺は　家族と思ってたこいつに裏切られて傷ついたわけだ
I was a kid, and thought it was family. I felt hurt and betrayed.
以上
That’s it. No big deal.
大した話しじゃない
There must be a reason it didn’t talk.
しゃべらないのはきっと理由があるんじゃないかな
I agree.
私もそう思います
It doesn’t look so broken down.
彼はそこまで壊れている状態には見えません
I know.
分かってるよ
四五年もすりゃ　俺もガキなりに察しがつくようになったさ
I was only four or five years old,
but I could guess what was going on.
My dad ordered it to stop talking.
親父が命令したんだ
Told it not to talk under any circumstance.
何があってもしゃべるなってな
俺とこいつを引き離そうとしたんだろう
He tried to drive us apart.
Just like something my dad would do.
親父のやりそうなこった
Orders from parents get priority.
親の命令は優先される
Masaki-kun, you’re very perceptive.
真崎君は聡明でらっしゃる
“Perceptive”?
聡明って
ガキの頃は分かんなかったんだよ
I didn’t know that when I was a kid!
I kept trying to talk with it!
こいつとまた話すためなら何でもした
I even cried and apologized!
泣いて謝ったこともあんだぜ俺は
If commanded, it can ignore a crying, wailing child.
命令されりゃ　泣き喚く子供だって無視できんだよ
For years.
何年もな
結局
Ultimately,
they can’t understand people’s hearts!
こいつらは人の心なんて分かりやしないんだ
簡易調査にアンドロイドを使用します
“… use androids in the cursory investigation.”
イヴの時間って店があってさ
“This café called Time of Eve … I go there too …”
俺も行ってるから　人のこと言えねぇけどさ
“Record all androids and humans … urge arrests.”
現場で目撃した人間　アンドロイドすべてを記録
検挙を促します
消し去るべき場所だ
“… should be eliminated.”
今から　こ…この店のルールをや…破ります
I am going to br-break th-this café’s rule.
You are in violation of Robot Law 9, Article 3.
あなたはロボット法第九条第三項に抵触しています
According to data in my possession, you are an android.
なぜなら私の保持するデータによると　あなたはアンドロイドであり
アンドロイドが起動中にリングを消すのは
If an android deactivates its ring while still active,
ロボット法違反に当たるからです
it is in violation of robot law.
なんだよこれ
What’s going on?
なんでテックスがしゃべってんだよ
Why is Tex speaking?
親父の命令はどうなってんだ
What about Dad’s command?
A command.
命令
命令を破る
It’s breaking a command.
Breaking the Second Law …
第二条を破る
第二条を破れるのは第一条だけ
… is permitted only in upholding the First Law.
第一条　危険
The First Law means … danger?
誰が
A human here is in danger?
人間が
この場にいる人間が危険
いや　テックスが人間だと分かるのはこの場では俺だけ
Can’t be. Who does Tex know to be human?
Only I.
俺が危険
だから俺を守るために
I’m in danger?
Tex is speaking … to protect me?
しゃべる
よって　あなたの管理者に対し法的措置を講じる必要があります
Hence, it is necessary to take legal action against your owner.
あなたの管理者の情報を求めます
I require your owner’s information.
本調査と倫理委員会の関係を極秘事項にするよう
“We will issue absolute orders to the android investigators; they must keep their ties with our committee a secret.”
絶対命令を徹底します
真崎君
マサキ
Masaki!
I’m not letting go!
放さねぇぞ
Unless you … unless you talk to me,
お前が　お前が俺にしゃべるまで放さねぇぞ
I’m not letting go!
Tell me!
教えてくれ
What were you thinking?
お前は何を思ってた
For so many years.
何年もずっと
All that time.
Watching me … all those years.
ずっと
ずっと俺を見てきて
俺の傍にいて
You were right there with me.
Tex, help me!
テックス　助けてくれ
俺に声をかけてくれよ
Speak to me!
I couldn’t speak to you.
話しかけることはできなくて
I always wanted to be at your side.
ずっと傍にいたくて
I …
私
私は
I …
ずっと
… always …
マサカズ君のことを
Masakazu-kun—
He wanted to protect you.
この子　真崎君を守りたかったんじゃないかな
分かってるよんなこと
I know that much.
危険が去ったらしゃべれない
It won’t speak once the danger has passed.
こいつはまだ親父の命令に縛られたままだ
It’s still bound by Dad’s command.
お前も分かってほしかったのか
You wanted me to understand too, huh?
でもな　やっぱ納得できねぇよ
But, even so, I can’t accept this.
今は無理かもしれないけど
It might be impossible now,
いつかきっとしゃべれるようになるよ
but someday, surely, it will talk.
適当なこと言うな
Don’t just say things.
I didn’t.
違うんだ
It’s not like I don’t have a reason.
理由がないんじゃなくて
But I can’t express it well.
うまく言えないけど
I’ve seen so many things here.
ここでいろんなこと見てきて
問題は色々あるけど
There’re many problems.
その都度悩んで
It’s distressing to see them each time.
でも
But this feels like the right path.
進んでる方向は間違ってない気がするんだ
マサキもだって同じだよ
It’s the same for you, Masaki.
I’m sure.
だから　きっと
You might be right.
そうかもな
I’ll tell Dad that I brought you out of the house.
親父には俺が連れ出したことにしとくぞ
私は
I … always … Masakazu-kun …
ずっと
マサカズ君のことを
Let’s go home.
帰ろうぜ
How did it get in?
どうやって入ったんだ
I held it.
抱えて
I lifted it up.
持ち上げて
ったく世話焼かせやがって
You really are demanding a lot!
Someday I’ll get you to thank me for today.
いつか今日の礼を言わせてやるからな
I love everyone.
みんな大好き
I’m so happy we can all be here.
嬉しいの
ここにいることができて
They’re going home together!
一緒に帰ってるよ
It’s all right.
It’s all right.　いいの
手助けするべきでしたか
Should I have helped them?
No. It’s enough that you watched over them.
いえ　見届ければそれでいい
It might have developed into another dangerous incident.
また危険な事件に発展する可能性もありました
I’m sure Shiotsuki understands that much.
潮月ならそれくらい分かってるはず
But is this really related to Shiotsuki-shi?
そもそも本当に潮月氏と関係があるのですか
That café’s rule …
あの店のルール
Indeed, it was 1138.
確かに1138です
1138.
我が国のロボット法すら上回る命令優先コード
The Priority Order code that can even override our country’s robot laws.
That would make sense.
これで説明がつくはずよ
Code:life’s deterrent circuit isn’t working.
code:LIFEの抑制回路が機能しない
すべてあの時間のために
This is all to prepare for that time.
Time of Eve’s rule
In this café,
there is no discrimination
between humans and robots.
Customers, please cooperate.
Obey the rule and have a fun time…
Could anyone else but Shiotsuki have done it?
そんなことできる人間が潮月以外に
しかし
But—
One more thing.
もう一つ
Android control taken to new extremes
トキサカ事件　当時の記事ですか
An article about the Tokisaka
Incident, from when it happened?
No, this is …
いや　これは…
It’s the real article, before the contents were replaced.
配信間際で差し替えられた本当の記事
If this girl, five years old at the time, is by chance still alive …
当時五歳の少女
仮にまだ生きているとすれば
Time of Eve
Retain
I forgot to bring out your Evlend today.
今日はイヴレンド出しそびれちゃった
なんか物足りないと思った
I thought something was missing.
テックスってどうやってこの店に来たんだろう
How did Tex get to the café?
You don’t know?
あら分かんない?
You do?
知ってるの
I thought you were a regular here.
もうすっかり常連だと思ってたのに
Rikuo-kun, you’ve got a long way to go.
リクオ君もまだまだね
ま…まだまだですか
Still a long way?
Huh? Someone new?
新入りさん?
I’m going to say hello.
ちょっと挨拶してくるね
これが僕のイヴの時間での物語り
This is my tale of the Time of Eve.
Welcome!
いらっしゃいませ
Take any seat that’s free!
空いてる席にどうぞ
I’ll take your order soon.
注文取りに行くから
僕はこのあともここでいろんな体験をするんだけど
Many more things happened to me, but …
You might not be here for long, but enjoy yourself!
短い時間かもしれないけど　楽しんでってね
… that’s another story.
それはまた別のお話し
ko
u
e
n
no
be
n
chi
de
wa
ra
t
te
i
ta
We were laughing on the park bench
公園のベンチで笑っていた
kouen no benchi de waratteita
坐在公园的长椅上微笑
公園のベンチで笑っていた
natsu no asa
夏日的清晨
夏の朝
na
tsu
no
a
sa
that summer morning
夏の朝　草原が緑に輝いてた
so
u
ge
n
ga
mi
do
ri
ni
ka
ga
ya
i
te
ta
and the grass was shining green
sougen ga midori ni kagayaiteta
草地的绿色闪耀着光芒
草原が緑に輝いてた
ho
n
to
u
ga
mi
e
na
i
ki
mi
no
hi
to
mi
What color are your eyes
ほんとうは見えない君の瞳　どんな色
hontou wa mienai
无法看透你的双眸
ほんとうは見えない
kimi no hitomi donna iro
有着怎样的颜色
君の瞳どんな色
do
n
na
i
ro
that don't see the truth?
ki
mi
ga
te
ru
so
ra
o
mi
tsu
ke
ta
ku
te
I want to find the sky you see
君が見てる空を見つけたくて
kimi ga miteru sora wo mitsuketakute
想寻找你所仰望的那片天空
君が見てる空を見つけたくて
I
have
a
dream
I have a dream
sasayaka sugite totemo
非常渺小
ささやかすぎてとても
sa
ya
ka
su
gi
te
A very modest one
ささやかすぎてとても
to
te
mo
ki
mi
ni
i
e
so
u
ni
wa
na
i
ke
re
do
Even if I can't tell you about it
kimi ni iesou ni wa nai keredo
无法对你说出口
君に言えそうにはない けれど
君に言えそうにはないけれど
a
sa
ga
ku
ru
me
o
ko
su
ri
Morning comes, rubbing my eyes
朝が来る　目をこすり
asa ga kuru me wo kosuri
清晨醒来 睡眼惺忪
朝が来る　目をこすり
hi
to
go
mi
o
a
ru
i
te
ku
I walk through the crowd
人混みを歩いてく
hitogomi wo aruiteku
踱步在人群中
人混みを歩いてく
ku
ri
ka
e
su
hi
bi
no
na
ka
in these repeating days
繰り返す日々の中
kurikaesu hibi no naka
在不断重复的日子里
繰り返す日々の中
chi
i
sa
na
yu
me
o
sa
ga
shi
tsu
zu
ke
ru
I keep searching for a little dream
小さな夢を探し続ける
chiisana yume wo sagashi tsudzukeru
不断追寻那小小的梦想
小さな夢を探し続ける
sol
te
i
mar
ti
a
ses
ta
i
mar
ti
a
kon
te
si
mi
a
to
i
si
ri
a
vi
to
mi
a
kon
te
i
mar
ti
a
ses
ta
i
mar
ti
a
kon
te
i
mi
a
sa
si
ri
a
do
che
i
vis
ta
to
ki
wa
yu
ku
bo
ta
chi
wa
su
re
chi
ga
i
ma
ta
de
a
u
Time goes by, we miss each other and meet again
時は行く　僕達は　すれ違い　また出会う
toki wa yuku bokutachi wa
时光流逝 我们
時は行く 僕達は
surechigai mata deau
擦身而过 又再次相遇
すれ違い　また出会う
ko
go
e
te
ta
fu
yu
no
hi
o
ka
mi
shi
me
te
reflecting upon the frozen day of winter
kogoeteta fuyu no hi wo kamishimete
细细品味严寒的冬日
凍えてた冬の日をかみしめて
a
sa
ga
ku
ru
ka
ze
ga
fu
ku
Morning comes, the wind is blowing
朝が来る　風が吹く
asa ga kuru kaze ga fuku
清晨来临 微风习习
朝が来る　風が吹く
hitogomi wo aruiteku
踱步在人群中
人混みを歩いてく
hi
to
go
mi
o
a
ru
i
te
ku
I walk through the crowd
人混みを歩いてく
ki
mi
no
ta
me
bo
ku
no
ta
me
for you, for me
君のため　僕のため
kimi no tame boku no tame
为了你 为了自己
君のため　僕のため
sekai wa yume wo tsumugi tsudzukeru
世界继续编制梦想
世界は夢を紡ぎ続ける
se
ka
i
wa
yu
me
o
tsu
mu
gi
tsu
zu
ke
ru
the world keeps spinning dreams
世界は夢を紡ぎ続ける
ただいま
I’m back.
まだ大丈夫そう
Looks like things are fine.
苦労かけるね
You’ve worked hard.
Though it doesn’t smell like salt,
塩の香りはしないけど
I still like the current café.
今の店も好きよ
It’s in the city, so lots of people gather there.
町だからいろんな子が集まるの
みんな元気かい
Is everyone doing well?
うん
悲しい顔してる
You look sad.
She …
あの子が
芦森に壊されてからずっと
Ever since Ashimori broke her,
不安なんだ
I’ve been feeling insecure.
They—
みんな
幸せになれるのかな
Will they find happiness?
No matter how many times we try …
何回試しても
今度の場所　何度目だ?
This time round—how many times has it been now?
三度目
Three times …
Or four …
四度目
みんな
They—
笑えるようになるのか
Will they be able to laugh?
I—
僕は
Your children are laughing …
あなたの子供たちは笑ってる
Alongside humans.
人間と一緒に
不安で
I feel insecure.
たまらないんだ
It’s unbearable.
大丈夫
It’s all right.
Someday, definitely, it will extend beyond the café.
いつかきっとお店だけじゃなくて
今日ねそう思えることがあったの
Something happened today to make me think that.
Won’t you tell me about it?
聞かせてくれないか
The main character is a certain boy.
主人公はある男の子
だから今日のお話はね
So today’s story is …